RAKESH BADGUJAR

313-329-8749 ♦ ☑ rakeshbadgujar31@gmail.com ♦ in www.linkedin.com/in/rakeshbadgujar ♦ ❷ rakeshbadgujar.github.io ❷ www.github.com/rakeshbadgujar ♦ ❸ 12561, Bagley Way, Parker, CO 80134

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Full Stack Developer with 9+ years of versatile experience in all parts of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) including agile, requirement analysis, design specification, code development, code integration, testing and deployment of client-server applications using Object Oriented Analysis Design (OOAD) and scalable API solutions.

SKILLS

Languages: Java, J2EE, Python, C++, SQL, PL/SQL, JavaScript, Typescript, HTML5, CSS.

Framework/Tools: SpringBoot, Node.js, Asp.Net, Angular 17, React, Django, MVC, Git, BitBucket, Spark, MySQL, Linux, Spring, Apache Tomcat, Maven, JUnit, Serverless Computing (Lambda and Azure Function), NoSQL, Gradle, JPA, Redis, Postgres, AppDynamics, Dynatrace, PCF applications, Checkmarx scan, Splunk, Kibana, IntelliJ, Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Rabbit MQ, Kafka, JSON, Cassandra, Postman, mongoDB, SonarQube, Elasticsearch, JWT, Hibernate ORM, Azure CI/CD.

Platforms: Linux, Windows, AWS (EC2, S3, Lambda, RedShift), Azure, Google cloud platform (GCP).

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer, Mastercard, O'Fallon, Missouri

March 2022 - Present

- Leading project for implementing Tap to provision functionality for cardholders to add their cards to digital wallets by tapping on back of the phone, Improved verification process compared to manual entry, leading to 80% fewer errors and increased security.
- Developing asynchronous RESTful Microservices using Spring Boot to facilitate tokenized transactions using InControl Virtual Card Numbers (VCNs) on digital devices which generated \$30m in revenue for Mastercard.
- Developing a mapping system to manage spend controls by mapping transactions to VCNs, expected to add \$15 billion in processed Gross Dollar Volume for Mastercard in the first two years.
- Collaborating with a cross functional team, we are developing a functionality aimed at splitting the current 6-digit Bank Identification Numbers (BINs) into 8-digit ones, in response to the escalating transaction demands within the banking sector.
- Developing user stories using Spring boot microservices to process the messages into the Kafka cluster setup, leading to a 40% reduction in message processing latency.
- Developing a custom locator service to determine the transaction region by appending a suffix to the account number, Achieved a 100% compliance rate with government requirements by accurately determining transaction regions for all accounts.
- Worked on pass migration of 2 billion tokens from third-party TSPs to MDES, addressing immediate business needs.
- Achieving a 30% reduction in database query response times by optimizing transactions and diagnostics using AppDynamics.
- Increasing application performance by 25% through identifying and resolving bottlenecks using Dynatrace.
- Integrating Jenkins with Azure CI/CD pipelines for automated testing and deployment, enabling continuous delivery.
- Enhancing database management by managing Cassandra clusters on AWS, resulting in 70% improvement in database efficiency.
- Implementing cluster services using Kubernetes and Docker to manage local deployments in Kubernetes by building a self hosted Kubernetes cluster using Terraform and Ansible and deploying application containers.
- Mentoring junior developers in Java best practices and design patterns, resulting in a 30% improvement in code quality and adherence to coding standards across the team through code review.

Senior Software Engineer, ULINE, Pleasant Prairie, Wisconsin

Nov 2021 - March 2022

- Developed quote 2.0 project, decomposing monolithic architecture into microservices on cloud platforms, Leveraged horizontal scaling capabilities of PCF, reducing infrastructure lead time by 7-8 months and lowering operational costs by 40%.
- Developed CI/CD pipeline for the ULIN's online shopping application, the time-to-market for new features and enhancements is improved by 80%.
- Implemented an ISO service equivalent to RAM API, Achieved a 60% increase in transaction security and performance for remote commerce transactions of ULINE e-commerce platform.
- Developed secure payment gateway built using Spring Boot, providing authentication services for various use cases including card addition, consumer profile verification, and token binding.
- Worked on user profile monitoring project demonstrating the implementation of design patterns such as Singleton, Factory, DAO, Session Facade, Front Controller, and Delegate Pattern.
- Developed messaging module using Spring JMS, Apache Camel, and RabbitMQ, improved the integration capabilities of the system.
- Developed customer tracking application built using React.js that allows users to create, manage, and track their account activity. This project demonstrates the use of React components, forms, events, keys, router, animations, and Flux architecture.
- Implemented a complete automated build release solution using a combination of technologies and tools as GitHub, Webpack, NPM, MsBuild, Maven, Jenkins and Power shell scripts.
- Worked on build/deploy tools such as Jenkins, Docker, Azure Devops, SonarQube, Urban Code for Continuous Integration & Deployment for Microservices.

Senior Software Engineer, Missouri State Courts Administrator, Jefferson City, Missouri June 2021 - Nov 2021

- Developed suite of applications to manage various aspects of court proceedings, Achieved 60% coverage of required functionalities, including alphabetic indexes, judgment indexes, docket sheets, court calendars, public access.
- Migrated the application from cloud Foundry to AWS using the EC2 and Fargate instances, Streamlined court proceedings and administrative tasks through automation, resulting in a 80% improvement in efficiency compared to the previous system.
- Developed automatic case number assignment and citation number using Spring Boot, Node is, Angular 17, and React forms.
- Used a Microservices architecture using Clojure, with Spring Boot-based services interacting through a combination of REST and Rabbit MQ or Apache Kafka message brokers.
- Leveraged MySQL and DynamoDB for storing and managing court-related data and electronic transfers, ensuring flexibility and scalability of 3 million records.
- Worked on AWS Lambda to manage the servers and run the code in the AWS and Automation of various administrative tasks.
- Implemented Elasticsearch, Splunk, and Kibana for real-time monitoring and analysis of court proceedings and administrative tasks, enabling identification of bottlenecks and areas for improvement
- Integrated Checkmarx scan and SonarQube for code analysis and security scanning

Software Development Engineer III, DATATRAK International Inc, College Station, Texas Aug 2018 - June 2021

- Developed Electronic Data Capture (EDC) project aims to provide a streamlined and cost-effective solution for launching clinical trials quickly, particularly for Pre-Clinical, Phase I, and II studies, Achieved a 70% reduction in clinical trial launch time.
- Developed a cloud-based PMS solution to streamline post-market surveillance, increasing efficiencies for Phase IV requirements and reducing manual efforts by 40%.
- Developed Spring Boot services for backend logic and data management, facilitating secure access to imaging data and endpoint adjudication workflows. Utilized Docker and Kubernetes for handling large volumes of imaging data.
- Supported all types of protocol randomization requirements, ensuring balance and eliminating selection bias, resulting in a 60% improvement in supply fulfillment accuracy.
- Developed rich frontend interfaces using Angular 7 and React, providing users with interactive and intuitive trial design experience.
- Implemented powerful reporting features, allowing study teams to access, filter, and export real-time study data into clear and concise reports, resulting in a 80% reduction in reporting time.
- Developed a unique process allowing teams to implement mid-study changes without any study downtime or data migration, resulting in a 60% increase in study flexibility
- Implemented JSON-based APIs for seamless interaction with external systems and used Postman for API testing and validation
- Collaborated with Trial Designers to enhance the end-user experience by providing extensive trial design capabilities, resulting in a 80% increase in user satisfaction.
- Wrote automated test scripts (TDD and BDD) using Selenium and TestNG framework in java.

Software Development Engineer, Autozone, Memphis, Tennessee

Jan 2017 - June 2018

- Developed real-time inventory tracking and management using Springboot, MySQL database and JPA, reducing the occurrence of overselling by 70%.
- Integrated secure payment gateways to facilitate online transactions, resulting in a 90% increase in successful payments and reduced instances of payment errors.
- Utilized Kafka for order management, enabling efficient processing of orders and reducing order processing time by 70%.
- Developed content management capabilities to publish product descriptions, specifications, images, videos, user reviews, and other relevant information.
- Developed Golang based web services on AWS and Google App Engine.
- Developed reporting features to generate insights, identify trends, and make data-driven decisions to optimize e-commerce operations.

Software Developer, Accede Software Solutions, Pune, India

Jan 2015 - July 2016

- Enhanced application performance by 20% through meticulous code profiling, identifying and resolving performance bottlenecks in Java applications.
- Boosted database query efficiency by 35% by optimizing SQL queries and implementing caching mechanisms, resulting in faster data retrieval and processing.
- Achieved a test coverage increase of 40% by implementing comprehensive unit tests and integration tests using JUnit and Mockito frameworks, ensuring robustness and reliability of Java applications.

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University, Kingsville, Texas Master of Science Computer Science University of Pune, Pune, India Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Engineering

May 2018 Cumulative GPA: 3.66

May 2015 Cumulative GPA: 3.52

HONORS & AWARDS